If you will change, everything will change for you.
You don't have to change what's outside.
All you've got to change is what's inside.
To have more, you simply have to become more.
And then he said, don't wish it was easier.
Wish you were better.
Don't wish for less problems.
Wish for more skills.
Start working on yourself, making these personal changes.
And he said, it'll all change for you.
So let's talk a little bit about personal development.
That extraordinary adventure I undertook starting at age 25.
And I've never ceased that adventure.
I'm still going for it in the 90s.
I want to get better and better.
I want my craft to get
better, my business operations to get better,
the things I do to get better.
Because once I picked up the simple formula,
I'm telling you it's easy to figure out where
the problem is if you go to work on it.
Now, let's talk about personal development.
And in helping kids understand personal
development, I always start with money.
Now, money is not the only place to start.
Money certainly isn't the only value,
but we've all got to start somewhere.
Money is something you can count.
Kids are interested in money.
A lot of things are a little tougher to measure.
But economics is pretty easy, right?
Because you can count.
Somebody says, how are you doing?
I don't know.
Let's count.
Now, this is not the only way.
You can only count.
I understand that.
There's a lot of other things to count.
But to see if there may be some errors
in your judgment and lack of disciplines in your life,
we might as well start with money.
Because it's so easy to count.
So let's just start there and see
whether or not maybe we have messed up.
Okay.
So here's how I explain it to kids.
We get paid for bringing value to the marketplace.
Key to understanding economics.
Marketplace is also described as reality.
Reality, the marketplace.
Now, it takes time.
It takes time to bring value to the marketplace.
But we don't get paid for time.
It's very important for kids
to understand, as well as adults.
We don't get paid for time.
Mistakenly, the man says, well, I'm
making about $20 for an hour.
Not true.
If that was true, you could just
stay home, have them send your money.
No, it's not true.
You don't get paid for the hour.
You get paid for the
value you put in the time.
So we don't get paid for time.
We get paid for value.
Now, since that's true, here's one
of the key questions of the afternoon.
Is it possible to become twice as valuable?
And make twice as much money in the same time?
Is it possible to become three
times as valuable as you now are?
And make three times as
much money in the same time?
Is that possible?
Of course.
If you want to really emphasize
something, that's a good phrase to it.
Of course.
Okay.
Now.
All you have to do.
To earn more money in the same time.
Is simply become more valuable.
America's unique.
It's a ladder to climb.
Starts down here.
What?
About $4 an hour.
Big argument.
Last year in Congress.
About the starting place.
Should be five.
Well, no.
It doesn't need to be five.
Why not start with four?
It's a ladder.
Right.
This is not a bed.
This is a ladder.
It's a ladder to climb.
Starts at $4.
Now somebody said, well, should be five.
Should be five.
Well, maybe.
If you're going to stay at the bottom for
the rest of your life, it probably should be five.
But that's kind of a pitiful way to live.
Start and not grow.
Start and not change.
Start and not become more valuable.
Hey, the whole scenario of life is to start.
Start number one and what?
Become more valuable number two.
So America is a ladder to climb.
Starts at $4 an hour.
And the more valuable you become,
you just keep moving up the ladder.
Top income last year.
What?
Fifty two million.
Guy that runs Disney.
Would a company pay somebody for one year's work?
Fifty two million dollars.
And the answer is, of course, this
is one of those, of course, places.
Of course.
If you help a company make
a billion dollars, would they pay you?
Fifty two million?
The answer is, of course, it's chicken feed.
I mean, it's not much money.
Now, why that much money?
Because he has become so valuable.
Now, why would we pay
somebody only four dollars an hour?
They're not very valuable to the marketplace.
Now, we've got to make that distinction to the marketplace.
Might be a valuable brother,
a valuable member of the community,
valuable member of the church, valuable
member in the sight of God,
to the human family, of course, those kind of values.
But to the marketplace, which is called what?
Reality.
Reality is if you're not very
valuable, you don't get much money.
Those are called the facts.
I mean, that's how that is.
But the reality is,
if you're not very valuable, you don't get much money.
Well, then how do you get more money?
Simple answer.
Somebody says, well, I'll go on strike for more.
Well, here's a major problem with that.
Here's a major problem with that.
You can't get rich by demand.
Somebody says, well, I'm waiting for a raise.
I'm telling you, it's easier to
climb than to wait for a raise.
Why not just become more valuable?
Well, rather than wait, I'm telling you,
that's the key to all good things.
Becoming more valuable.
Why would we pay somebody $400 an hour?
They've become more valuable to the marketplace.
See how this works?
I'm telling you, this stuff is so easy.
This is America.
This is a ladder.
How far is it from four to five?
I'm telling you, it's not far.
Four to $5 an hour.
If you work for McDonald's, haul out
the trash, they'll pay you $5 an hour.
If you whistle while you haul out
I'm telling you, you'll get an
extra dollar just for a good attitude.
Yay, McDonald's.
Wear the hat.
Incredible.
And then you just keep becoming
more valuable, more valuable, more valuable.
I got a telephone call five years ago.
Company said, we're ready to expand.
We need some help.
I was sort of semi-retired.
Looking for the next exotic beach.
They said, no, no, Mr. Rohn,
we got a project for you.
Going to expand internationally.
We could use your help.
Next little while, we'll add some millions
to your fortune, make it worth your while.
I said, okay.
I thought later, isn't that interesting that they called me?
I said, okay. I thought later,
isn't that interesting that they called me?
My second thought was, of course they'd call me.
Who else would they call?
I mean, you know, I can get the job done.
Now, how come I got a telephone call worth millions?
I had become valuable.
Now, I'm a farm boy from Idaho.
I was raised in obscurity.
One year of college, and
I thought I was thoroughly educated.
Made all kinds of mistakes galore.
At age 25, the creditors are calling me saying,
hey, you told us the check was in the mail.
I got pennies in my pocket.
I got nothing in the bank.
I'm behind on my promises.
How come I get a telephone call
five years ago and it's worth millions?
I changed.
I turned my life around.
Is it possible to become worth millions?
Speaking economically, now, there's a lot of
values to become, but let's just talk economics.
Is it possible to become that valuable?
And the answer is, of course.
Of course.
Now, let me give you the secret.
Shoaff said, here's the secret, Mr. Rohn.
Learn to work harder on your life.
Learn to work harder on yourself
than you do on your job.
Once I got that, it turned my life around.
Learn to work harder on yourself
than you do on your job.
He said, if you work hard
on your job, you'll make a living.
If you work hard on
yourself, you can make a fortune.
Wow.
If you would have known me at age 25,
you would have said, Jim Rohn's a hard worker.
If you'd have known me, you'd have said that.
I'm the guy, I don't mind coming a
little bit early, staying a little bit late.
I don't mind that.
You'd have said, well, Jim Rohn's a hard worker.
You'd say, well, how come he's got pennies in his
pocket and nothing in the bank and behind on his promises?
Well, I was a hard worker, but I
was working hard on my job, not on myself.
I'm telling you, if you'll learn that simple little principle and start
the process today, latest tomorrow, I'll give you tonight to think it over.
And start this whole process of personal development, work
on yourself, make yourself more valuable to the marketplace.
I'm telling you, you can so dynamically change your income and economics is
the least of the values that you can start earning in terms of equity.
If you'll start working harder on yourself than you do
on your job, work hard on yourself and develop the skills.
Work hard on yourself and develop the graces.
All of the stuff necessary to
become more valuable to the marketplace.
I'm telling you, your whole life can explode into change.
Promotions, no problem.
Becoming more valuable to the
company, I'm telling you, no problem.
Money, no problem.
Economics, no problem.
Future, no problem.
If you just go to work on the right thing.
Not get things out there to change.
Don't try to change the seed.
Don't change the soil.
Don't change the sunshine.
Don't change the rain.
Don't change the mix of seasons.
Let the miracle of everything that's available work for you.
And start working on the inside.
Work on your philosophy.
Work on your attitude.
Work on your personality.
Work on your language.
Work on the gift of communication.
Work on all of your abilities.
And if you'll start making those personal changes,
I'm telling you, everything will change for you.
Now, let me give you another.